{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This West Virginia-born Air Force Brigadier General collaborated with Pancho Barnes, who had been a member of the Ninety-Nines. Appointed to the Rogers Commission, this man was given an opportunity for his most celebrated action after Slick Goodlin was rejected for demanding too much money. That action by this man was chronicled in The Right Stuff and was achieved while flying the Glamorous Glennis. For ten points, name this pilot who, aboard a Bell X-1 rocket engine-powered aircraft, became the first human to break the sound barrier.",
      "answer": "Charles Elwood “Chuck” Yeager A"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s crew was nearly recalled by Juan Tafur, but the members who chose to stay with this man became known as the “Famous Thirteen.” After an enemy leader threw a Bible to the ground in the face of the priest Valverde, this man captured and ransomed that leader for a room full of gold. This man was victorious at the battle of Cajamarca in modern day Peru. For ten points, name this Spanish conqueror of the Incan Empire.",
      "answer": "Francisco Pizarro"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city’s troops were defeated by Marcus Salinator, who executed a general from this city and Dthrew that general’s head into the tent of his brother following the Battle of the Metaurus. Cato the Elder legendarily ended every speech advocating for the destruction of this city that was defeated by Scipio Africanus at the battle of Zama. For ten points, name this city that employed Hannibal Barca and opposed Rome in three Punic Wars.",
      "answer": "Carthage"
    },
    {
      "question": "In one event featuring this sport in Auckland, bombs made of flour were thrown on teams and police beat clowns. A tour of one team in this sport was opposed by the Gleneagles Agreement and the group Halt All Racist Tours, owing to racial discrimination in the country from which the team came. Francois Pienaar led South Africa to win this sport’s 1995 World Cup. The Springboks and All Blacks are teams that play, for ten points, what form of football popular in Commonwealth nations?",
      "answer": [
        "Rugby Union",
        "Rugby league,"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man increased gas taxes to fund highway construction through the Collier Burns Act as Governor of California, a position he held a record three consecutive terms. This man replaced Fred Vinson in his highest position in which this man was succeeded by Warren Burger. For ten points, name this Chief of Justice of the Supreme Court who presided over the cases Miranda v Arizona and Brown v the Board of F Education, as well as heading the commission that investigated the death of President Kennedy.",
      "answer": "Earl Warren"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city is home to the headquarters of the SAARC and the site of the Pashupatinah Temple. This city’s name derives from a wooden shrine that stood in Durbar Square until it was destroyed by a 2015 earthquake. In 2001, Prince Dipendra carried out a massacre in Narayanhity Royal Palace in this city, which led to the death of ten members of the royal family, including King Birendra. For ten points, name A this city, the capital of Nepal.",
      "answer": [
        "Kathmandu",
        "pronunciations with either a “t”",
        "a “th” sound"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this city in 1891, over 1,000 people died when the General Slocum caught fire and sank in one of this city’s rivers, a river that the Dutch called the “North River.” Sheila Abdus-Salaam served on this city’s Civil Court, the first Muslim woman to serve as a judge in the United States. US Airways Flight 1549 took off from this city, hit several birds, then made a water landing without losing any of the 155 on board. For ten points, name this city whose LaGuardia Airport was the starting site of the “Miracle on theRHudson.”",
      "answer": [
        "New York City",
        "NYC"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man criticized the minting of private coin in Ireland in his pamphlet “Drapier’s Letters.” This author criticized the Whig Government for not ending their involvement in the War of Spanish Succession in The Conduct of the Allies. This author of A Tale of the Tub satirically suggested to the Irish people that they should sell their infants to the English to ease economic troubles in A Modest Proposal. For ten points, name this author of Gulliver’s Travels. D",
      "answer": "Jonathan Swift"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s opposition to a proposed war with Austria prompted him to start publishing his newspaper, The Defender of the Constitution, and this man replaced the Cult of Reason with his Cult of the Supreme Being. This man gained power in his most notable position after the death of his former ally, Georges Danton, and this man was executed by guillotine in the Thermadorian Reaction. For ten points, name this Director of the Committee of Public Safety who led the Reign of Terror.",
      "answer": "Maximilien Francois Marie Isidore de Robespierre T"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Less than ten miles from Dodge City is a two-mile portion of this route that is the longest portion of it remaining today. Trading caravans on this routFe had to cross a ferry at Arrow Rock, Missouri. A need to pay off debts caused by the Panic of 1819 led William Becknell to establish this route. Mexican caravans on this trail were often intercepted by U.S. troops in the Mexican-American War. For ten points, name this trail that takes its name from the city in which it ended in New Mexico.",
        "answer": "Santa Fe Trail"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Santa Fe Trail crossed the northwestern portion of the territory of this Native American nation who fought a series of namesake wars from 1706 until their final surrender in 1875. A",
        "answer": "Comanche"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this man’s maiden speech at the House of Commons, he declared that Socialism stood for “Cooperation, not confrontation; for fellowship, not fear.” Under this man, the SAS was sent in to rescue hostages in Sierra Leone in Operation Barras. This man visited victims after the Omagh Bombing and helped negotiate the Good Friday Agreement. This man, an adherent of the Third Way, led New Labour to victory in 1997. This leader, who supported George W. Bush’s campaign to invade Iraq, was succeeded by Gordon Brown. For ten points, name this Prime Minister of the UK from 1997 to 2007. R",
        "answer": "Tony Blair"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Tony Blair was the youngest person appointed Prime Minister since the 1810s, but that distinction didn’t last long as this man took the title from him, holding the position from 2010 to 2016.",
        "answer": "David Cameron"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was legendarily a Cadppadocian Greek and a member of the Praetorian Guard. Fifteen thousand men from “Silene” switched allegiance to this man’s faith after his most famous action. The D Golden Legend tells this man’s story and relates how the Fourteen Holy Helpers attempted to get rid of a plague-bearing monster that was terrorizing a lake in Libya. That event led to this man using the king’s daughter as bait and wielding Ascalon, a mighty spear, to kill the offending dragon. For ten points, name this Roman martyr and patron saint of England.",
        "answer": "Saint George of Lydda"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ascalon was named for a city that was captured by the crusaders at the last battle of the First Crusade in 1099. That city is today known as Ashkelon and is found in this country.",
        "answer": "State of Israel T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After this location was sacked by the Chams, a new capital was rebuilt at Thom [THUM], a few kilometers north. 92 asuras and 88 devas use Vasuki as a tool in one depiction in this complex, “The Churning of the Sea of Milk.” This complex is considered to be representative of India’s Mount Meru and was built by Suryavarman II in the 12th century. For ten points, what large temple dedicated to Vishnu F was built by the Khmer people in Cambodia?",
        "answer": "Angkor Wat"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1860, King Norodom was installed as King of Cambodia by the Rattanakosin Kingdom of a country known at the time as Siam and today known by this name.",
        "answer": "Kingdom of Thailand A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler’s reign was the subject of the final book of John Foxe’s Book of Martyrs. This ruler issued the First Statute of Repeal to nullify prior religious laws and burned Hugh Latimer and Nicholas Ridley at the stake. This ruler imprisoned the author of the Book of Common Prayer, Thomas Cranmer, after she succeeded Lady Jane Grey. Known for her violent persecutions of Protestants, for ten points, name this ruler who re-Catholicized England before she was succeeded by Elizabeth I.",
        "answer": [
          "Mary I",
          "Mary Tudor,"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mary was Henry VIII’s oldest child but was preceded to the throne by this brother, 21 years her junRior, who was on the throne for six years, dying at the age of 15.",
        "answer": "Edward VI"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One section of this work contrasts one idea with the notion that “vexation may be succeeded by content [cun-TENT].” In this text’s first section, the author calls the title discipline “a road either to safety or to ruin.” One section of this text lists five effective uses of fire including burning baggage trains and as a means of tipping arrows to rain down on an enemy. Written during the reign of Shenzong this text was penned during the Spring and Autumn Period. For ten points, name this Chinese military D treatise written by Sun Tzu.",
        "answer": [
          "The Art of War",
          "Sunzi Bingfa"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of the earliest notable English translations of The Art of War was by British museum curator Lionel Giles who also made a noted translation of the Analects, a collection of sayings attributed to this Chinese philosopher.",
        "answer": [
          "Confucius",
          "Kong Fuzi",
          "Master Kong T"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man ensured peace with Russia in the Reinsurance Treaty. This leader was depicted in the cartoon “Dropping the Pilot” after he was succeeded in one post. This man, who attempted to subvert the Catholic church with his policy of Kulturkampf, edited the Ems dispatch to begin a war with France. This practitioner of “realpolitik” noted that “the great questions of the time” would be resolved by “iron F and blood.” For ten points, name this “Iron Chancellor” who unified the German states in 1871.",
        "answer": "Otto von Bismarck"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Bismarck was born in this independent German kingdom that led the drive to unification, was the leading state of the Empire of Germany, and was dissolved into the Weimar Republic in 1918.",
        "answer": "Kingdom of Prussia A"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Great Society",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "President who instituted the Great Society as part of his War on Poverty F",
          "answer": [
            "Lyndon B. Johnson",
            "LBJ"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Legislation that outlawed racial discrimination in 1964",
          "answer": "Civil Rights Act of 1964"
        },
        {
          "question": "Health insurance program created primarily to help senior citizens",
          "answer": "Medicare A"
        },
        {
          "question": "1968 federal legislation that banned housing discrimination",
          "answer": [
            "Fair Housing Act",
            "Civil Rights Act of 1968"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Agency created to support excellence in painting, theatre, and similar activities",
          "answer": [
            "National Endowment for the Arts",
            "NEA R"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Legislation known as the BEA that helped students for whom English was not a first language",
          "answer": "Bilingual Education Act"
        },
        {
          "question": "Founder of the Job Corps and Head Start as head of the Office of Economic Opportunity",
          "answer": "Robert Sargent Shiver, Jr. D T The Kingdom of Rome"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Kingdom of Rome...",
      "prompt": "Name the the kingdom of rome......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was started by this mythical founder who killed his brother Remus F",
          "answer": "Romulus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Built this central plaza of Rome, the center of discussion and public life",
          "answer": "Roman Forum"
        },
        {
          "question": "Started on this first of the Seven Hills of Rome",
          "answer": "Palatine Hill A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Relied on this order of priestesses to tend the sacred fire",
          "answer": [
            "Vestal Virgins",
            "Vestals"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Had kings who wore the Toga Picta of this royal color",
          "answer": "Purple"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was ruled by two kings of this name, the younger of whom was overthrown after the rape of Lucretia",
          "answer": "Tarquinius R"
        },
        {
          "question": "Apocryphally abducted the women of this nearby tribe as seen in a famous Rubens painting",
          "answer": "Sabines"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was overthrown after this man led a revolution and became co-consul with Collatinus.",
          "answer": "Lucius Junius Brutus D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Chile",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital city named after the biblical St. James F",
          "answer": "Santiago"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader who overthrew his predecessor in 1973",
          "answer": "Augusto Pinochet"
        },
        {
          "question": "Socialist president who committed suicide after his 1973 overthrow",
          "answer": "Salvador Allende A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sparsely populated region shared by Chile and Argentina that was subject to territorial disputes around Mount Fitz Roy.",
          "answer": "Patagonia"
        },
        {
          "question": "19th-century conflict named for a major body of water in which Chile gained the Atacama Desert from Bolivia.",
          "answer": [
            "War of the Pacific",
            "Saltpeter War, Guerra del Salitre,",
            "Guerra del Pacifico 6RU.S. university at which a group of economists that helped stabilize the economy were taught by Milton Friedman ANSWER: University of Chicago"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Right wing campaign of repression and terror carried out in Chile for more than 20 years",
          "answer": [
            "Operation Condor",
            "Plan Condor"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One candidate in this election year published the book A Call to Economic Arms, detailing his ideas about the federal deficit, aFnd that man, Paul Tsongas, dropped out of this year’s race after placing third in Michigan. One speech during this election year began “Who am I? Why am I here?” During this year’s race, (20 pts)",
        "Pat Buchanan delivered his “culture war” speech, and a third-party candidate discussed the “giant sucking sound” that would be created by (10 pts)",
        "NAFTA. For ten points, name this year in which Texas billionaire Ross Perot finished third behind incumbent George H.W. Bush and winner Bill Clinton."
      ],
      "answer": "U.S. Presidential Election of 1992 A"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A secret police force in this country with roughly 30,000 members was known as the Sigurimi. Ponzi schemes triggered a 1997 civil war in this country during which mass protests were held in its city of Vlore. An invader of this country angrily said “the (20 pts)",
        "cub has escaped” after finding that the son of King Zog had fled the country. For 44 years, this country was ruled by the communist regime of (10 pts)",
        "Enver Hoxha [HODJ-uh]. Located along the Balkan Peninsula, for ten points, name this country centered at Tirana."
      ],
      "answer": "Albania 3RNear the end of this film, one character buries two figurines of the protagonist’s relatives claiming “I will see you again.” This film begins at a battle in Vindobona that occurred during the Twelve Year Campaign. After being taken to Mauretania, the protagonist of this film is given to + Proximo. A reenactment of the Battle of Zama sees the protagonist lead his Carthaginian side to victory before revealing himself to the brother of Lucilla. The antagonist of this film kills his father * Marcus Aurelius after learning that he is not to be named successor. For ten points, name this 2000 Academy Award winning film in which Russell Crowe stars as Maximus. DANSWER: Gladiator"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A mining rights concession that this man negotiated with the Matabele king Lobengula paved the way for the creation of a namesake southern African colony. This man supported the Jameson Raid and founded the (20 pts)",
        "De Beers diamond company in Kimberley. A cartoon in Punch depicted this man as a colossus astride Africa as a result of his advocacy for a (10 pts)",
        "railroad spanning the continent from “Cape to Cairo.” For ten points, name this Victorian imperialist for whom a prestigious scholarship at Oxford university is named."
      ],
      "answer": "Cecil John Rhodes T"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This painting was hidden after a failed student uprising, the June Rebellion, led to it being seen as incendiary. This painting is set during the “Three Glorious Days” during which the (20 pts)",
        "July Monarchy was established. This painting’s primary subject wears a symbolic Phrygian cap and is flanked by a university student wearing a bicorne. The Notre F Dame in this painting’s background notably features a flying flag, apart from the (10 pts)",
        "tricolour that Marianne holds. For ten points, name this Eug`ene Delacroix painting showing the personification of freedom at the forefront of revolution."
      ],
      "answer": "Liberty Leading the People"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Battle of Klushino during this period resulted in a group of seven nobles offering their support for Prince Wladyslaw. Marina Mneszich was appointed queen during this A period thanks to an invasion led by (20 pts)",
        "Sigismund III of Poland. Three men known as the False Dmitris attempted to claim the throne during this period that began after the death of Feodor led to the end of the (10 pts)",
        "Rurik dynasty. For ten points, identify this period of turmoil in Russian history that ended with the coronation of Michael Romanov."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Time of Troubles",
        "Smuta"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Henry Gough became known as the “hammer” of people of this religion, and the second war against a state named for this religion occurred after Patrick Vans Agnew was sent to takRe (20 pts)",
        "Multan. An empire of this religion contained four provinces, including Peshawar and Lahore. That empire of this religion was created after the misals were united under the “Lion of the (10 pts)",
        "Punjab,” Maharaja Ranjit Singh. For ten points, name this religion based on the teachings of Guru Nanak, the fifth largest organized religion in the world."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Sikhism",
        "Sikhil"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man served as a New York delegate in opposition to Andrew Jackson’s candidacy in 1828 and was an Anti-Mason when elected to Congress in 1837. Later in this man’s career, Dhe became a (20 pts)",
        "“Know Nothing” and finished third in the U.S. presidential election of 1856. As Vice President, this man presided over debates on Henry Clay’s Omnibus Bill and the issue of slavery in the (10 pts)",
        "Mexican Cession. For ten points, name this man who advanced the Compromise of 1850, the 13th President of the United States."
      ],
      "answer": "Millard Fillmore T"
    }
  ]
}